<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- $Id$ -->

<article>
    <articleinfo>
        <title>GridSphere Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    </articleinfo>

    <title>GridSphere Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <para>
    This section contains a few Q's and A's on installing and configuring GridSphere
    </para>
    <qandaset defaultlabel="qanda">
        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    I'm using JDK 1.4.1 and when the build script tries to build the docbook target it fails with:
                    <literallayout>[style] : Fatal Error! org.apache.xml.dtm.DTMException:
No more DTM IDs are available Cause: org.apache.xml.dtm.DTMException:
No more DTM IDs are available</literallayout>
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para>
For some reason the version of Xalan shipped with JDK1.4.1 has some bugs.
The recommended solution is to get a recent xalan.jar from http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/index.html to
                    <filename>$JAVA_HOME/jre/lib/endorsed</filename>. (If you have an Apple with OS X then copy it to
                    <filename>/System/Library/Frameworks/JavaVM.framework/Home/lib/endorsed/</filename>)
                </para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    I would like to add support for a new locale in GridSphere. What must I do?
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para><important>Make sure you check GridSphere out of CVS to get latest files!</important></para>
                <para>
                 First translate the following two GridSphere property files:
                 <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <filename>gridsphere/config/resources/Portlet_en.properties</filename>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/WEB-INF/classes/Portlet_en.properties</filename>
                    </listitem>
                 </orderedlist>
                    Use the appropriate ISO language code e.g. English is "en", Spanish is "es", etc. in the filename.
                    The properties are Unicode encoded, which means you should create a temp file with the properties
                    in the native language complete with accents, etc. Then you need to run "native2ascii" tool that
                    is distributed with JDK on the temp file. E.g. <emphasis>native2ascii mytranslation > Portlet_hi.properties</emphasis>
                    as an example of translating to Hindi.
                </para>
                <para>
                 Second translate the following descriptor files:
                 <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/WEB-INF/portlet.xml</filename>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/WEB-INF/layout.xml</filename>
                    </listitem>
                     <listitem>
                        <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/WEB-INF/authmodules.xml</filename>
                    </listitem>
                 </orderedlist>
                 These files are UTF-8 encoded. Simply editing them in most IDE's or JEdit is fine.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Now you must create a flag icon in <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/images/flags</filename>
                    directory. look at existing flags for proper sizing and filename conventions.
                </para>
                <para>
                   Finally edit <filename>gridsphere/webapps/gridsphere/WEB-INF/GridSphereServices.xml</filename> and in
                    the section for the "Locale Service", add your locale to the comma separated list of supported locales.
                </para>
                <para><important>Please send us your additions so we can add them back into the code!</important></para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>

        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    Why is it called GridSphere-- I don't see anything Grid related in it!
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para>
                GridSphere provides a complete portal framework based upon the portlet
                API and a minimal set of core portlets. To provide greater reusability and flexibility,
                it was decided to not require any Grid
                services for the proper functioning of the GridSphere portlet container. However, we are currently
                developing many fundamental Grid portlets that will showcase GridLab and OGSA services under a
                separate portlet application "grid portlets".
                </para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>


        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    I think I found a bug or I have a feature request!
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para>
                 See our bugtracker at:

                            <ulink url="http://bugs.gridsphere.org">http://bugs.gridsphere.org</ulink> .

                </para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>


        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    I'm having problems what should I do?
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para>
                Please join the mailing lists!
                    <simplelist>
                        <member>
                            <ulink url="https://www.gridlab.org/mailman/listinfo/gridsphere-users">gridsphere-users</ulink>
                                - Discussion for gridsphere users
                        </member>
                        <member>
                            <ulink url="https://www.gridlab.org/mailman/listinfo/gridsphere-dev">gridsphere-dev</ulink>
                                - Discussion for gridsphere developers
                        </member>
                    </simplelist>
                </para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>


        <qandaentry>
            <question>
                <para>
                    I started my own portlets package and deployed it. Gridsphere now fails loading at startup!
                    I think I edited all configuration files correctly. What's wrong?
                </para>
            </question>
            <answer>
                <para>
                Please doublecheck the xml configuration files and make sure that the packagename of the portlets
                contains '.portlets.' and of the services '.services.'.
                </para>
            </answer>
        </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>

</article>
