
<!--

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

    Author:     Jason Novotny
    Version:    $Id$
-->

<chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    The GridSphere Administrator's Guide describes how to administer the running GridSphere portal.
    For more information on installing and developing  portlets, please consult
    the GridSphere User's Guide and the GridSphere Tutorials. This guide assumes you have succesfully installed
    GridSphere.
    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Editing administrator profile</title>
        <para>
            When you startup GridSphere for the first time, you may login as the super user with the user name
            <emphasis>root</emphasis> and an empty password. Now click on the Administration tab and then go to the
            Users tab. Here you can select the <emphasis>root</emphasis> entry and edit your profile. At the minimum,
            you should change the password and enter a valid email address. This email will be used in the case that
            a portlet group is made private on the portal and a user wants to obtain membership.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Creating new users and restricting account creation</title>
        <para>
            From the Users tab as the super user, you can create also create/modify/remove users from the portal.
            By default, when the portal is first initialized, anyone can create a new account for themselves from the
            login screen. If you wish to restrict new account creation to the portal administrator, then go to the
            Administration=>Portlets tab to teh "Configure Login" portlet. Here you can select to restrict new account
            creation if desired.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Editing group information</title>
        <para>
            The Administration=>Groups tab shows the "Group Manager" portlet that displays all the known portlet groups.
            Portlet groups can be dynamically created and are associated with a collection of portlets. In addition a group defines
            access rights for the portlets, and a flag to indicate
            which groups are public and private. Normally a new user has access only to the
            GridSphere group but may join additional groups via the "Profile Manager" portlet in the Welcome=>Settings
            tab. Users may immediately join any groups that are public on the portal. If the group is private, then the
            user has the option to request group submission from the portal administrator by sending an email request.
        </para>
        <para>
            A user that is granted the ADMIN role, an administrator,  when logged in will also have access to the "Group Manager" portlet.
            An administrator has the capability to add and remove users to the group they are administrator of as well as
 creating and editing groups on the portal.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Portlet administration</title>
        <para>
            The Administration=>Portlets tab displays the "Portlet Application Manager" portlet that displays the
            status of all known portlet groups. An admin may stop or restart a portlet group as well as deploy new
            portlet web applications to the portal. These features use the Tomcat manager web application to
            perform web application reloading and initialization. If the portlet web application is a GridSphere/WebSphere
            application then reloading will not work if the application contains any portlet services,
            since the service classes that are deployed to <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/shared/lib</filename>
            may not be restarted by the manager web application. In this case, the best is to redeploy the portlet
            application from the command line. If the portlet application is JSR compliant, then redeploying the
            webapp via the "Portlet Application Manager" should work fine since all classes including service classes
            are contained within the classloader of the webapp and no classes are deployed to <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/shared/lib</filename>.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Layout Administration</title>
        <para>
            The Administartion=>Layouts tab offers the "Layout Manager Portlet" that allows an administartor to modify the
            layout of a particular group. Currently, the layout descriptor must be hand edited in the text area and then saved.
            The changes will take place when a user logs out and logs back in. This offers a simple yet effective way to edity the guest
            user layout or the layouts of defined groups. In addition, the banner of the portal may be edited as well allowing
            an admin to change the portal header including logo and title information.
        </para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>
