
<!--

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

    Author:     Jason Novotny
    Version:    $Id$
-->

<chapter id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    The GridSphere Administrator's Guide describes how to administer the running GridSphere portal.
    For more information on installing and developing  portlets, please consult
    the GridSphere User's Guide and the GridSphere Tutorials. This guide assumes you have succesfully installed
    GridSphere.
    </para>

    <sect1>
        <title>Editing administrator profile</title>
        <para>
            When you startup GridSphere for the first time, you may login as the super user with the user name
            <emphasis>root</emphasis> and an empty password. Now click on the Administration tab and then go to the
            Users tab. Here you can select the <emphasis>root</emphasis> entry and edit your profile. At the minimum,
            you should change the password and enter a valid email address. This email will be used in the case that
            a portlet group is made private on the portal and a user wants to obtain membership.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Creating new users and restricting account creation</title>
        <para>
            From the Users tab as the super user, you can create also create/modify/remove users from the portal.
            By default, when the portal is first initialized, anyone can create a new account for themselves from the
            login screen. If you wish to restrict new account creation to the portal administrator, then go to the
            Administration=>Portlets tab to teh "Configure Login" portlet. Here you can select to restrict new account
            creation if desired.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Editing group information</title>
        <para>
            The Administration=>Groups tab shows the "Group Manager" portlet that displays all the known portlet groups.
            A portlet group is associated with a portlet web application and the administrator can configure
            which groups are public and private. Normally a new user has access only to the
            GridSphere group but may join additional groups via the "Profile Manager" portlet in the Welcome=>Settings
            tab. Users may immediately join any groups that are public on the portal. If the group is private, then the
            user has the option to request group submission from the portal administrator by sending an email request.
        </para>
        <para>
            A user that is granted the ADMIN role, an administrator,  when logged in will also have access to the "Group Manager" portlet.
            An administrator has the capability to add and remove users to the group they are administrator of.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Portlet administration</title>
        <para>
            The Administration=>Portlets tab displays the "Portlet Application Manager" portlet that displays the
            status of all known portlet groups. An admin may stop or restart a portlet group as well as deploy new
            portlet web applications to the portal. These features use the Tomcat manager web application to
            perform web application reloading and initialization. If a portlet web application has any portlet services,
            these features will not work, since the service classes that are deployed to $CATALINA_HOME/shared/lib
            may not be restarted by the manager web application. We'll be working on this in a future release. For now,
            this portlet is useful if your webapp is a simple collection of portlets and no portlet services. Otherwise,
            you are better off restarting the portal from the command line if portlet re-initialization is desired.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Portlet administration</title>
        <para>
            The Administration=>Portlets tab displays the "Portlet Application Manager" portlet that displays the
            status of all known portlet groups. An admin may stop or restart a portlet group as well as deploy new
            portlet web applications to the portal. These features use the Tomcat manager web application to
            perform web application reloading and initialization. If a portlet web application has any portlet services,
            these features will not work, since the service classes that are deployed to
            <filename>$CATALINA_HOME/shared/lib</filename>
            may not be restarted by the manager web application. We'll be working on this in a future release. For now,
            this portlet is useful if your webapp is a simple collection of portlets and no portlet services. Otherwise,
            you are better off restarting the portal from the command line if portlet re-initialization is desired.
        </para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Portlet subscription and customization</title>
        <para>
            When deploying new portlets to the portal, there are two ways to import them into your layout. For full
            customization, you must go to the Welcome=>Subscription tab to the "Subscription" portlet. This allows
            you to select/deselect the portlets in your subscription. After that, you can go to the Welcome=>Layout
            tab to the "Layout Manager" portlet and you now have the ability to create/modify/remove tabs and portlets
            associated with tabs. The second approach is to click on the <emphasis>Reset layout</emphasis> button in
            the "Layout Manager" portlet and this will reset your layout according to group membership and destroy
            any customizations that were made previously.
        </para>
    </sect1>

</chapter>
